Finding Aid for the Albert Boime Papers LSC.1834
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert Boime papers
1941-2008
UCLA Library Special Collections
Boime, Albert
LSC.1834
64.8 Linear Feet (151 boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 2 shoe boxes, and 1 carton)
The collection contains drafts, correspondence, notes, course materials, research aids, CVs, and audiovisual materials pertaining to the academic career of art historian and professor Albert Boime. Materials in the collection span Boime's graduate studies and lengthy career, including seminal research on Vincent Van Gogh, Impressionism and the French Commune, and a 6-volume History of Modern Art written from a social history perspective. Though best known for his work on 18th and 19th century European art, Boime's papers cover a broad range of traditional and avant-garde Art History topics approached from a social history theoretical framework.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL, AUDIO, AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Digital, audio, and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Myra Boime, 2007, 2010.
2010 addition consisted of 2 cartons containing film reels, video, audio, 1 notebook.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9967001553606533
Biography/History
Albert Boime was born in St. Louis, Missouri on March 17, 1933 to Max and Dorothy Boime, both eastern European Jewish immigrants. In 1955 Boime joined the U.S. Army, serving in Germany before his discharge in 1958. Upon returning to the States Boime began his studies at the University of California, Los Angeles and received his B.A. in 1961. He went on to receive both his M.A. (1963) and Doctorate (1968) from Columbia University. Through his brother Jerome (1934-1977), Boime met teacher and social activist Myra Block, and they married in 1964.
He began his career as an instructor at the State University of New York at Stony Brook in 1967 and became an associate professor in 1969. He was appointed professor of art at the State University of New York at Binghamton in 1971. Boime chaired the art department at Binghamton from 1972-74 and was recruited by the University of California, Los Angeles in 1978. He served as a professor of art history there for three decades. Boime passed away in 2008.
As a social art historian Boime was concerned with overlooked artists and ventured outside traditional research methods to evaluate an artist's work. He approached artworks as social documents, not simply artistic expressions, and demonstrated how artists are influenced by the historical events of their lifetime. Though Boime is best known for his studies of 19th-century European art, his work touched on many genres including popular imagery in Europe and America and emblematic national monuments.
In the course of his career Boime authored nearly 20 books and over 100 articles. He also received various awards including two Guggenheim fellowships (1974, 1984), a Rome Fellowship (1979), and the A. Kingsley Porter Prize for his Art Bulletin article "The Second Republic's Contest for the Figure of the Republic" (1971). In 2006 a symposium on the social history of art was convened at UCLA in his honor.
Quoting from the preface of his book The Birth of Abstract Romanticism, Boime described his art historical intent, "By examining the political forces that motivated the art makers and finders, and revealing the hidden mainsprings in visual production, I truly believed that I was contributing to the emancipation of thought, at least in one small corner of the minds of my students and readers. Thus art history became my raison d'être, a vehicle for enhancing the lives of my fellow citizens, while at the same time bringing about a nano-change toward social justice in society."
Sources: Dictionary of Art Historians, albertboime.com
Scope and Content
The collection consists of notes, correspondence, drafts, and annotated photocopies relating to Boime's academic career. Additional materials include VHS tapes, audiocassettes, and 16mm film. The papers include documentation corresponding to universities and Art History departments where he was employed, syllabi and outlines for courses and seminars, notes associated with research, conference materials, drafts of publications, and correspondence. The bulk of the collection consists of materials collected as part of Boime's research activities. Research topics span a wide range, although the bulk of material relates to French history painter Thomas Couture, imagery and symbolism of U.S. monuments and icons, artists and movements associated with his Social History of Modern Art series, social issues, academies and academic painting, the Italian painter group Macchiaioli, and comics and cartoons. Boime often revisited research topics after initially encountering the subject matter, so his files may include materials from different decades on the same research topic. The addition contains similar materials and subjects, and a greater number of audiovisual materials. Box 154 contains film reels that were digitized and documentation from the processing archivist, Chloe Patton.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Career, 1950-2005
Subseries 1.1: Academic life, 1950-2005
Subseries 1.2: Fellowships and grants, 1973-2002
Subseries 1.3: Department affairs, 1970-2004
Subseries 1.4: Special projects, 1975-2003
Subseries 1.5: Colleagues, 1980-2003
Subseries 1.6: Students, 1987-2003
Series 2: Course materials, 1978-2008
Series 3: Research materials, 1941-2008
Series 4: Lectures and conferences, 1972-2005
Series 5: Publications drafts, 1970-2004
Series 6: Correspondence, 1963-2008
Subseries 6.1: Publication correspondence, 1979-2007
Subseries 6.2: Specific correspondence, 1963-2003
Subseries 6.3: General correspondence, 1964-2008
Series 7: Audio and audiovisual materials, 1974-2005
Art historians -- United States -- Archives.; Boime, Albert--Archives.
- Series 1: Career, 1950-2005
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is comprised of materials relating to Boime's career as a professor of modern Art History. Most of the early files relate to Boime's high school and college studies, including coursework and yearbooks. The later files include materials related to Boime's faculty positions at SUNY Binghamton, Williams College, and UCLA. The series also includes documentation about fellowships and grants for which Boime applied, and special projects in which he participated. Lastly, the series encompasses correspondence, recommendations, and other materials relating to Boime's interactions with colleagues and students. The series is arranged by subject into six subseries, which are ordered chronologically.
  Arrangement
  Series is ordered chronologically.
  - Subseries 1.1: Academic life, 1950-2005
    This subseries contains material from Boime's high school and college studies, including high school yearbooks, college papers, and class notes. Of note is a selection of original cartoons created by Boime. It also include Boime's curriculum vitae and a history of his career as a professor.
    - High school yearbook 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Alexander Hamilton High School yearbook for class of 1950 (Boime's junior year) with signatures and inscriptions from classmates.
    - High school yearbook 1951 and notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Alexander Hamilton High School yearbook for class of 1951 (Boime's senior year) with signatures and inscriptions.
    - Student papers, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Copies of papers by Boime with comments and grades from professors.
    - Student papers, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Copies of papers "Van Gogh and Seurat: A Study of Stylistic Evolution," "Bipolarization: A Study of Diderot's Esthetic," "Comte, Maine, and the Law of Numbers," and "The Role of Claude's Figures." Also includes an Italian Architecture syllabus.
    - Student papers, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Copy of student paper "A Venetian Source for Lodovico Carracci, Guido Reni, and Guercino" for Professor Hibbard.
    - Class notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Notes and scribbles from Boime's courses on the Greeks/Classics and the Philosophy of Art. Also includes cartoons by Boime.
    - Cartoons, ca. 1960, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Originals and copies of cartoons by Boime submitted to the New Yorker, including rejection note from New Yorker.
    - Cartoons, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Original cartoons by Boime submitted to Laughs Unlimited.
    - Cartoons, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dream journal, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      A journal with entries describing Boime's dreams.
    - Dissertation notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Notes and outlines for Boime's PhD dissertation.
    - Boime's curriculum vitae and career history, 1984-2001 (Box 150, Folder 2-15)
  - Subseries 1.2: Fellowships and grants, 1973-2002
    This subseries includes applications, informational materials, and correspondence regarding a variety of grants, fellowships, and awards for which Boime applied during his career.
    - American Academy in Rome, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and fellowship information for Rome Prize from American Academy in Rome.
    - American Academy in Rome, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Draft of "The Spirit of the Place--Realism and Tradition in Venetian Ottocento Painting." Correspondence and application materials for fellowship at American Academy in Rome. Some materials in Italian.
    - American Academy in Rome - notes, ca. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Notes taken in Italian found within drawer containing, amongst other files, a file on Boime's fellowship with the American Academy in Rome. A receipt inside one of the notebooks is dated May 1980.
    - Film grant, 1973, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Drafts of application materials for a grant to fund an hour-length documentary film on contemporary American figurative painters. Correspondence and Boime's curriculum vitae.
    - Draft and proposal, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Proposal for museum tour program. Pages from unidentified draft with edits (topics include Lunar Society and Industrial Revolution).
    - National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Grant proposal, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      National Endowment for the Humanities Grant proposal for President's Research Fellowship to write "Art in an Age of Genocide, 1915-1989." NEH Evaluation sheet regarding Boime's proposed project.
    - Fellowships, 1974-1975, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Correspondence from the Guggenheim Foundation, SUNY Research Foundation application, and National Endowment for the Humanities Grant application (with budgets, project descriptions, and proposals). Other correspondence and Boime's curriculum vitae.
    - Grants, fellowships, etc., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Correspondence, drafts of budgets, statement of plans, and applications (for American Academy in Rome, Guggenheim Fellowship, and American Philosophical Society research grants).
    - Research grants, 1982-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, research funding application, Guggenheim fellowship information, and College Art Association conference materials.
    - Academic senate faculty grants, 1993, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      UCLA memos, information packets, and applications regarding research funding from UCLA Academic Senate Council on Research. Correspondence. Some materials are in Italian.
    - Chorafas, ca. 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and notes regarding nomination for a prize from the Dimitris N. Chorafas Foundation.
    - DTOAH letters, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Recommendation letters in support of Boime's nomination for a Distinguished Teaching Award from the College Art Association.
    - Myers award, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Myers Award presented to Albert Boime for Study of Human Rights in North America.
  - Subseries 1.3: Department affairs, 1970-2004
    This subseries encompasses internal university documents acquired through Boime's appointment as a faculty member at SUNY Binghamton, Williams College, and UCLA. The bulk of the subseries relates to Boime's teaching position at UCLA and includes subjects such as faculty promotions (including Boime's), university policies on sexual harassment and diversity, Art History curriculum changes, and advocacy by Boime on behalf of his students.
    - Binghamton, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Broome County Historical Society Newsletter.
    - Williams, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and notes, likely from Boime's research period at Williams College.
    - Department shit, 1976-2002, bulk 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and documentation regarding requirements for Boime's appointment to above-scale. Art History department meeting minutes, program and minor guidelines, and 1983 budget reports. University policy on sexual harassment and correspondence regarding student sexual harassment filing against professor Don Preziosi. Other topics include department revisions to accord with graduate review and financial aid disbursements. (File title assigned by Boime.)
    - Harassment file, 1988-1990, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      UCLA Memo regarding diversity issues. Correspondence and reports regarding Boime's appointment to above scale including Boime's response to departmental decisions. Correspondence regarding alleged prejudicial activities by department to Boime and his students. 1989 Teaching Assistant evaluations of Boime and correspondence regarding this matter. Inter-departmental correspondence regarding graduate students, committees, and faculty pay scale changes. (File title assigned by Boime.)
    - Boime faculty file, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Correspondence and documents in support of Boime's accomplishments; list of Boime's publications.
    - Faculty review file, 1992-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Correspondence generally supporting and emphasizing Boime's accomplishments as a scholar and educator. Some correspondence regarding Bram Dijkstra.
    - Department service, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and documents detailing Boime's professional accomplishments.
    - Name lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Lists of Boime's references outside UCLA.
    - Promotion review, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Review articles of Boime's books, copies of his articles, and correspondence regarding his assistance with lectures and other activities, likely all gathered as evidentiary support for Boime's promotion/salary review.
    - Department affairs, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Art History Department meeting minutes and agendas. Copies of letters in support of Boime's merit increase.
    - UCLA administration, 1970, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Notes, memos, and correspondence regarding university matters such as the closure of the word processing center, Dean's review committee, Art History department profile, and other department matters.
    - UCLA Art History, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Profile of UCLA Art History faculty and graduate students.
    - Art History department, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Paper entitled "Advertising and Experience in France, 1880-1918," author unknown. Department notices regarding foreign language examination requirements and PhD qualifying exam for Aaron Segal.
    - New general curriculum, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Proposal from faculty working group on new general education curriculum for UCLA. Report "Guidelines for Developing and Reporting Departmental Teaching Policies and Practices at UCLA." Honors Discussion Section Proposal Form. Brochure on information literacy at UCLA.
    - Art History department curriculum committees, 1991-2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Art History department meeting minutes. Reports from various curriculum committees on topics including teaching load, MA and PhD programs, undergraduate programs, and museum studies.
    - Art History department language requirement and minor, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Correspondence regarding language requirements for undergraduate major and proposals for revision to undergraduate art history degree requirements. Copy of UCLA Department of History Eight Year Review and proposal for an undergraduate minor in Art History.
    - Education-undergraduate, bulk 1992-1993, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Booklet from UC Faculty Conference on Undergraduate Education and clippings.
    - Faculty critical theory group, ca. 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Paper related to a presentation for Faculty Critical Theory Group.
  - Subseries 1.4: Special projects, 1975-2003
    This subseries encompasses work performed by Boime outside the scope of his university responsibilities as a professor. Materials include documentation regarding several court cases in which Boime served as an expert witness, materials for a festschrift in his honor, drafts of speeches and lectures, materials for a Bicentennial celebration of the French Revolution, and correspondence regarding special programs at the Smithsonian Institution.
    - Hart v. Warner Brothers court case, 1998-1999 (Box 132, Folder 1)
      Copies of depositions and remarks for court case over bas-relief on cathedral at Duke University campus. Brochures for Duke University, related papers and publications, and declarations in court case Hart, et al. v. Warner Bros, et al. for which Boime was a counselor.
    - Nash history project, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Proposal for Nash History Project: collaborative program between UCLA and the Getty Center offering supplementary History and Art Education teaching units to middle school teachers.
    - Yamagata and court case, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Newspaper clippings and copy of court proceedings for trademark case between Hard Rock Corporation and Martin Lawrence Galleries regarding a Hiroshi Yamagata painting. Photocopies from publication about Yamagata.
    - O'Melveny, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Correspondence and legal documents related to court case Hart, et al. v. Warner Bros, et al. spearheaded by O'Melveny & Myers LLP, for which Boime was a counselor. File includes numerous images and photographic reproductions regarding an art reproduction at the center of the lawsuit.
    - Boime fest, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Remarks for a conference for Boime (a Festschrift).
    - Jobs, 1998, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Notice and e-mail regarding academic job postings.
    - Interview, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Notes on interview questions and responses.
    - Smithsonian, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Correspondence with Louis Fink and Charles C. Eldredge, correspondence with Smithsonian regarding Regents Fellowship and notes. Copy of National Endowment for the Humanities grant application from Helene Roberts.
    - Bicentennial program, ca. 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Notes and documents regarding UCLA's French Revolution bicentennial program.
    - In memoriam, ca. 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Drafts of eulogy and speech, invitations to funerals, and various speech materials for graduations and symposia.
    - Graduation talks, ca. 1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Drafts of graduation speeches.
    - Expenses and bills, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding payments and invoices for academic work.
    - Reader reports, 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Copies of Boime's reports as a reader of other scholars' material for Kent State Press and Princeton University Press. Some correspondence.
    - Questionnaires, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Author questionnaires from publishers with Boime's responses.
    - Disney exchange, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Correspondence regarding anti-Semitism in "Newsies."
  - Subseries 1.5: Colleagues, 1980-2003
    This subseries is comprised of materials relating to Boime's correspondence and service to academic colleagues. Most materials are publications by colleagues that were submitted to Boime for his review and commentary. Colleagues include David Galenson, Bram Dijkstra, Andrew Brainerd, and Barry Shifman. There are also student and colleague recommendations composed by Boime. The subseries is arranged by colleague, beginning with the largest volume of material.
    - Photos, undated (Box 132, Folder 2)
      Photos of Boime with colleagues and correspondence (probably from subject in photo).
    - Galenson manuscript (1 of 2), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Manuscript for "The Careers of Modern Artists: A Quantitative Analysis" by David Galenson with edits by Boime.
    - Galenson manuscript (2 of 2), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Dijkstra manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Manuscript of "America and Georgia O'Keeffe" by Bram Dijkstra.
    - Dijkstra, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Form letter regarding Bram Dijkstra's academic review at UC San Diego.
    - Dijkstra, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      E-mail correspondence and copy of "Review of Bram Dijkstra's Book 'American Expressionism: Art and Social Change 1920-1950" by Boime.
    - Brainerd-book, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Correspondence with Andrew Brainerd, drafts of chapters 1, 2, and 4 to untitled volume (presumably written by Andrew Brainerd) with edits by Boime.
    - Brainerd, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Photocopies and copy of Boime's paper "Manet's Lost Infanta" in collaboration with Alexander Kossolapov. Correspondence related to Brainerd's research and publication "The Rise of Reason in the Authentication of Fine Art: New Perspectives on Connoisseurship in a Disillusioned World."
    - Shifman draft, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and draft of work by Barry Shifman for Boime's review: "Depictions of French Royal and Imperial Chateaux in the Decorative Arts: An Iconographic Study."
    - Barry Shifman draft, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Note from Barry Shifman and draft of his paper "Depictions of Chateaux in the Decorative Arts: Symbols for Propaganda" with edits
    - Barry Shifman materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Copy of paper on European Ornament Prints by Barry Shifman. Catalogue entries and introduction for exhibition on European Ornament Prints.
    - Duro file, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Correspondence regarding Paul Duro. File includes Duro's curriculum vitae, letters of recommendation, transcript, and summary of academic interests.
    - Patricia McGinn, 1991-1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Eulogy for Patricia McGinn, correspondence, and materials regarding McGinn Memorial Fellowship.
    - Liverpool, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Critique of proposal by Jonathan Harris (likely at University of Liverpool). Proposal not included with materials.
    - Curriculum vitae, 1980, 1984, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and curriculum vitae for Boime to compose recommendations.
    - Tenure letters, 1986, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Recommendation letters composed by Boime endorsing colleagues for tenure. Colleagues include Leonard Folgarait, Jonathan Ribner, and Barbara Ann Day.
    - Letters of recommendation, 1984-1992, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Boime's letters of recommendation for students and colleagues. Selected student curriculum vitae and papers.
    - Guggenheim recommendations, 1987-2002 (Box 6, Folder 10)